<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- <!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" -->
<!-- "http://www.sonatype.com/tmp/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"> -->
<chapter id="misc">
<title>
Oher build tricks
</title>
<para>
This chapter discusses topics that are often discussed in the context of Tycho such as bundle signing, running quality analysis tools.    
</para>

<section>
<title>
Signing bundles 
</title>
<para>
The signature of bundles and features is recommended for Eclipse applications. The signature will be checked at install time by p2.
</para>
<para>
To enable signing, the Maven plugin called maven-jar-signing can be used. TO FILL (refernece and sample).
</para>
</section>

<section>
	<title>
		Generating JavaDoc
	</title>
	<para>
		Javadoc generation is covered by using the standard maven-javadoc-plugin
		(http://maven.apache.org/plugins/maven-javadoc-plugin/) along with all
		its configuration options. The most simple example would be to execute

		mvn javadoc:javadoc

		which will create javadoc for each module in target/apidocs/.
		
		Note that this does not cause the generation of the javadoc for extension and extension points.
	</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>
Generating source bundles
</title>
<para>
Source bundle generation is switched on using the following snippet to be inserted in the build/plugins section of your (parent) POM:
</para>
<programlisting language="xml">
  &lt;!-- enable source bundle generation --&gt;
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.sonatype.tycho&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-osgi-source-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
        &lt;version&gt;$tycho-version&lt;/version&gt;
        &lt;executions&gt;
          &lt;execution&gt;
            &lt;id&gt;plugin-source&lt;/id&gt;
            &lt;goals&gt;
              &lt;goal&gt;plugin-source&lt;/goal&gt;
            &lt;/goals&gt;
          &lt;/execution&gt;
        &lt;/executions&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
</programlisting>
</section>

<para>
This will create an eclipse source bundle jar along with each bundle jar in the target/ folder of the module.
By convention, the source bundle SymbolicName is the bundle SymbolicName with ".source" appended.
Generated source bundles can then be included in a source feature which can be created just as any other feature. Automatic source feature generation may be added in a later version of Tycho.
</para>

<section>
<title>
Quality analysis tools
</title>
Running PMD
Running FindBugs
Running Emma (code coverage)
</section>

</chapter>